<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature, solemnity, grounds, property, and benefits, of a sacred covenant. Together with the duties of those who enter into such a covenant. Delivered in a sermon at Westminster, at the publique convention, (ordered by the Honourable House of Commons) for the taking of the Covenant, by all such, of all degrees, as willingly presented themselves, upon Friday, Octob. 6. 1643. By Ioseph Caryl, preacher to the Honourable Society of Lincolnes-Inne.</title>
            <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E72_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14164</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859623</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 12:E72[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature, solemnity, grounds, property, and benefits, of a sacred covenant. Together with the duties of those who enter into such a covenant. Delivered in a sermon at Westminster, at the publique convention, (ordered by the Honourable House of Commons) for the taking of the Covenant, by all such, of all degrees, as willingly presented themselves, upon Friday, Octob. 6. 1643. By Ioseph Caryl, preacher to the Honourable Society of Lincolnes-Inne.</title>
                  <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.G. for John Rothwell, and Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Sunne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "October 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Nehemiah IX, 38 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155471:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155471:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NATURE, SOLEMNITY, GROUNDS, PROPERTY, AND BENEFITS, Of a Sacred Covenant. TOGETHER WITH The duties of thoſe who enter into ſuch a COVENANT. Delivered in a Sermon at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> at that publique Convention, (ordered by the Honourable Houſe of Commons) for the taking of the Covenant, by all ſuch, of all degrees, as willingly preſented themſelves, upon Friday, <hi>Octob.</hi> 6. 1643. <hi>By</hi> IOSEPH CARYL, <hi>Preacher to the Honourable Society of Lincolnes-Inne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 2. 2, 3 4.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Kings of the earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take counſell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the Lord and againſt his anoynted, ſaying;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us breake their bands aſunder, and caſt away their coards from us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that ſitteth in the Heavens ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> and <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sunne in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:155471:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Sabbathi,</hi> 7 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1643.</head>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons houſe of Parliament, that Mr. <hi>Caryl</hi> be deſired to print his Sermon which he preached on Friday laſt at St. <hi>Margarets</hi> Church at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> upon the taking of the Covenant: And that Maſter <hi>Browne</hi> doe returne him thanks from this Houſe for his great paines therein. And further orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that none doe reprint his Sermon without his conſent.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <p>I Appoynt <hi>Iohn Rothwell</hi> and <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> to print my Sermon, <hi>Octob.</hi> 12. 1643.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. l. 1. <hi>for</hi> in, <hi>read</hi> is, p. 29. l. 33. <hi>for</hi> gloſſes, r. gloſſers, p, 36, l. 32. <hi>dele</hi> or.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:155471:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL THOSE WHO LOVE THE LORD JESUS CHRIST IN SINCERITY, AND Sincerely aſſociated themſelves in the bond of this holy COVENANT when this Sermon was preached; THE AUTHOR, Their unworthy, yet willing ſervant, in this or any other worke of the Lord, <hi>Humbly preſents this Sermon Printed:</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Heartily beſeeching God, our God, the great, the mighty, and the terrible GOD, who keepeth Covenant for ever, TO Strengthen us all, in performing all the duties, which we have promiſed in this Covenant.</p>
            <p>TO Fill us and theſe Kingdomes, with all the bleſſings, which this Covenant promiſeth, To the glory of his owne moſt holy name, the advancement of the Goſpell, in Peace and Truth, as the gracious returne of our preſent labours, and prayers, and the portion of our poſterity; that the children which are yet unborne may bleſſe us, and bleſſe God for us.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:155471:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155471:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON preached at the late Solemne Aſſembly, for the taking of the COVENANT, upon Friday the ſixt of this inſtant <hi>October.</hi> 1643.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>NEHEM. ch. 9. v. 38.</bibl> And becauſe of all this we make a ſure Covenant, and write it, and our Princes, our Levites, and our Prieſts ſeale unto it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He generall ſubject of this verſe in the ſpeciall buſineſſe of this day. A ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne engagement to the Lord, and among our ſelves, in a ſure Covenant. Wherein we may conſider theſe five things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the nature of a Covenant; from the whole.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the grounds of a Covenant, from thoſe words, <hi>Becauſe of all this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the property of a Covenant, in that Epithete, <hi>Sure, we make a ſure Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the parties entring into, and engaging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Covenant, expreſt by their ſeverall degrees and Functions. Princes, Levites, Prieſts. And were theſe all? All whom this Verſe ſpecifies, and enow to bring in all the reſt. Where the Governours and the Teachers go before in an holy example, what honeſt heart will not follow? And the next Chapter ſhewes us, all who were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:155471:4"/> honeſt-hearted, following this holy example, v. 28. <hi>And the reſt of the people, the Prieſts, the Levites, the Porters, the Singers, the Nethinims, and all they that had ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the people of the Lands unto the Law of God their Wives their ſons, and their daughters, every one having know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and having underſtanding.</hi> V. 29. <hi>They clave unto their brethren their Nobles, and entered into, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, The outward acts by which they teſtified their inward ſincere conſent, and engag'd themſelves to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue faithfull in that Covenant: Firſt, writing it. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſealing to it. Thirdly, (in the tenth Chapter, Verſe 29.) <hi>They entered into a curſe.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>into an Oath, to walke in Gods Law, which was given by Moſes the ſervant of God, and to obſerve to doe all the Commandements of the Lord their God with the Statutes and Iudgements. And that they would not give their daughters to the people of the Land,</hi> &amp;c. With divers other articles of that Covenant, tending both to their Eccleſiaſticall and Civill reformation.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt point, <hi>the nature of a Covenant.</hi> Concerning which, we may receive ſome light from the Notation of the originall words; 1. For a Covenant. 2. For the making of a Covenant. The Hebrew <hi>Berith</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Elegit, quia eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur perſonae inter quas &amp; res ac conditiones propter quas foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tur. Buxtorf,</hi>
               </note> (a Covenant) comes from <hi>Barah,</hi> which ſignifieth two things: Firſt, to chooſe exactly, and judiciouſly. Secondly, to eate moderately or ſparingly. And both theſe ſignifications of the roote <hi>Barah</hi> have an influence upon this derivative <hi>Berith,</hi> a Covenant; The former of theſe intimating, if not enforcing, that a Covenant is a worke of ſad and ſerious deliberation, for ſuch are ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive acts. Election is or ought to be made, upon the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall turne of judgement, not upon a catch of phancy, or the hurry of our paſſions.</p>
            <p>Now in a Covenant there is a double worke of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155471:4"/> Firſt, an election of the perſons, betweene whom. Secondly, an election of the conditions or termes upon which the Covenant is entered. <hi>As Gods Covenant-people are his choſen people, ſo muſt ours.</hi> Some perſons will not enter into covenant, though invited; and others, though they offer themſelves, are not to be admitted. They who are not fit to build with us, are not fit to ſweare with us. Some offered their helpe to the Iewes in the repaire of the Temple, <hi>(Ezr.</hi> 4. 2.) <hi>Let us build with you, for we ſeeke your God.</hi> But this tender of their ſervice was refuſed, Verſ. 3. <hi>Yee have nothing to doe with us, to build an houſe unto our God: but we our ſelves together will build, &amp;c.</hi> What ſhould we doe with their hands in the worke, whoſe hearts, we know, are not in the worke? The inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dment of ſuch in-joyning, muſt be either to build their <hi>Hay and Stubble</hi> with our <hi>Gold and Silver, and precious Stones,</hi> (1 Cor. 3. 12.) or elſe to pull downe by night, what they build by day, and ſecretly to undermine that Noble Fabricke, which ſeemingly they endeavoured to ſet up. We finde in this booke of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons combining in that Covenant were choice perſons. The Text of the tenth Chapter ſets two markes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction upon them. Verſ. 28. Firſt, <hi>all they that ſeparated themſelves from the people of the Lands, unto the Law of God.</hi> Secondly, <hi>all having knowledge, and having underſtanding.</hi> Here are two qualifications, whereof one is ſpirituall, and the other is naturall. The plaine Engliſh of both may be this. <hi>That Fooles and Malignants, ſuch as (in ſome meaſure) know not the cauſe, and ſuch as have no love at all to the cauſe ſhould be outcaſts from thu Covenant.</hi> Such ſapleſſe and rotten ſtuffe will but weaken, if not corrupt this ſacred band.</p>
            <p>The Tenour of the covenant now tendered, ſpeakes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155471:5"/> thus reſpecting the perſons. <hi>We Noble-men, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Commons, of all ſorts, in the Kingdome of England, Scotland, and Ireland &amp;c.</hi> And doth not this indiſtinctly admit all, and all, of all ſorts? I anſwer, No. For the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Preface ſhew expreſſely, that onely they are called to it, <hi>who are of one reformed Religion;</hi> which ſhuts out all Papiſts, till they returne. And the Articles paſſe them through a finer Sieve, admitting onely ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, yea and ſweare that through the grace of God, they will ſincerely, really, and conſtantly endeavour the preſervation of the reformed religion, againſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy in the one Kingdome, the reformation and extirpation of what is amiſſe in the other two; as alſo in their owne perſons, families and relations. They who doe thus are choice perſons indeed, and they who ſweare to doe thus are (in charity and juſtice) to be reputed ſo, till their owne acts and omiſſions falſifie their oathes. Thus our Covenant makes an equiualent, though not a formall or nominall election of the perſons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there muſt be a choice of conditions in a Covenant; As the perſons obliged, ſo the matter of the obligation muſt be diſtinct. This is ſo eminent in the Covenant offered, that I may ſpare my paines in the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it; every mans paines in reading of it, cannot but ſatisfie him that there are ſix Nationall conditions about which we make ſolemne oath, and one perſonall, about which we make a moſt ſolemne profeſſion and declaration before God and the world. And all theſe are choyce conditions: ſuch as may well be held forth to be (as indeed they are) the reſults and iſſues of many prayers, and ſerious conſultations, in both the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> Conditions they are, in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155471:5"/> which Holineſſe and Wiſdome, Piety and Policie, Zeale for God in purging his Church, and Care for man in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Common-wealth, appeare to have had (in a due ſubordination) their equall hand and ſhare.</p>
            <p>Thus much of a Covenant from the force of the word in the firſt ſenſe, leading us to the choice both of perſons and conditions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the root ſignifies to eat moderately, or ſo much as breaks our Faſt. And this refers alſo to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Covenant, which is to draw men into a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and holy communion, and converſe one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>David</hi> deſcribes <hi>a familiar friend, in whom he truſted,</hi> to be one, <hi>That did eat of his bread, Pſal.</hi> 41. 9. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when he would have a ſcandalous brother denied all fellowſhip in Church-Covenant, he charges it thus, <hi>With ſuch a one, no not to eat,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 11. Hence it was a cuſtome upon the making up of Covenants, for the parties covenanting ſoberly to feaſt together; when <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Abimilech ſware one to another, and made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> The ſacred Story tells us, that <hi>Iſaac made them a feaſt, and they did eat and drinke, Gen.</hi> 26. 29, 30. A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is a binder of affection, to aſſure it, but it is a looſner of affection, to expreſſe it. And their hearts are moſt free to one another, which are moſt bound to one another. How unbecomming is it that they who ſweare together, ſhould be ſo ſtrange as ſcarce to ſpeake toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? That which unites, ought alſo to multiply our affections.</p>
            <p>Further, the word hints, ſo to converſe together as not to ſinne together, for it ſignifies, Moderation in eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As if it would teach us, That at a <hi>Covenant-Feaſt,</hi> or when <hi>Covenanters feaſt,</hi> they ſhould have more <hi>grace</hi> then meat at their Tables: or if (through the bleſſing of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155471:6"/> God) their meat be much, their temperance ſhould be more. The Covenant yeelds us much buſineſſe, and calls to action; Exceſſe ſoyles our gifts and damps our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, fitting us for ſleepe, not for worke. In and by this Covenant we (who were almoſt carried into ſpirituall and corporall ſlavery) are called <hi>to ſtrive for the maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Let us therefore (as this word and the Apoſtles rule inſtruct us) <hi>Be temperate in all things,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 25. Intemperate exceſſive eaters will be but moderate wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, eſpecially in Covenant worke. A little will ſatisfie their Conſciences, who are given up to ſatisfie their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appetites. <hi>And he who makes his belly his God, will not make much of the glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much concerning the nature of a Covenant from the originall word, for a Covenant, ſignifying both to <hi>chuſe</hi> and to <hi>eate.</hi> We may take in ſome further light to diſcover the things from the orginall word, which we tranſlate <hi>(make) Let us make a Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That word ſignifies properly to <hi>cut,</hi> to <hi>ſtrike,</hi> or to <hi>ſlay.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The reaſon hereof is given, becauſe at the making of ſolemne Covenants, beaſts were killed and divided aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the Covenant-makers went between the parts. When God made that firſt grand Covenant with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, he ſaid unto him, Take an heifer of three yeers old, and a ſhee goat of three yeers old, &amp;c. And he tooke unto him all theſe, and divided them in the midſt, and laid thoſe pieces one againſt another, &amp;c. Gen.</hi> 15. 9, 10. At the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth verſe, <hi>Behold a ſmoaking furnace and a burning lamp</hi> (which latter was the token of Gods preſence for the deliverance of his people) <hi>paſſed betweene thoſe pieces.</hi> In the 34. of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> verſ. 18. we have the like ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in making a Covenant, <hi>They cut the calfe in twaine, and paſſed betweene the parts thereof.</hi> Upon this uſage the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155471:6"/> phraſe is grounded of <hi>cutting or ſtriking a Covenant, Pſal.</hi> 50. 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. 3. which Ceremony had this ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in it, That when they paſſed betweene thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided parts of the ſlaine beaſt, the action ſpake this curſe or imprecation, <note n="*" place="margin">Foedus facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes primò fura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, poſtea tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibant inter par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes pecudis; quaſi dicerent, diſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur, dividantur ejus membra, fiat ſicut pocus iſtud, qui furamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam violaverit.</note> 
               <hi>Let him be cut aſunder, let his members be divided, let him be made as this beaſt, who violates the Oath of this Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe obſervations about the words, we may be directed about the nature of the thing: and thence col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect this deſcription of a Covenant. <hi>A Covenant is a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne compact or agreement betweene two choſen parties or more, whereby with mutuall, free, and full conſent they binde themſelves upon ſelect conditions, tending to the glory of God and their common good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Covenant ſtrictly conſidered is more then a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and leſſe than a Oath; unleſſe an Oath be joyned with it, as was with that in the Text, and is with this we have now before us. A Covenant differs from a promiſe gradually and in the formalities of it, not naturally or in the ſubſtance of it. God made promiſes to <hi>Abraham; Gen.</hi> 12. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 13. but hee made no Covenant with him till Chap. 15. verſ. 18. <hi>In that day the Lord made a Covenant with Abraham.</hi> And the worke of the Lord in that day with <hi>Abraham</hi> had not onely truth and mercy in it, but ſtate and majeſtie in it. A Covenant day is a ſolemne day. As the collection of many Stars makes a <hi>Conſtellation</hi> ſo the collection of many promiſes makes a <hi>Covenant.</hi> Or as in the firſt of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> verſ. 10. <hi>The ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together of the waters, was by the Lord called Seas.</hi> So wee may call the gathering together of promiſes or conditions a <hi>Covenant.</hi> The Lord doth (as it were r'ally all the promiſes of mercy made to us, which lie ſcattered up and downe thorow the whole volume of the Scriptures,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155471:7"/> and puts them together into a Covenant: And we do (as it were) r'ally all the promiſes of duty which wee owe unto God and to one another, and put them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Covenant. Such a bundle of duty is tied up in this preſent Covenant; what duty is there which we owe to God, to his Churches, or theſe Common-wealths whereof we make not promiſe either expreſly or by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence in the compaſſe of this Covenant? And how great an obligation to duty doth this containe, wherein there is an obligation to every duty?</p>
            <p>Seeing then this Covenant being taken carries in it ſo great an obligation, it calls for great preparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we take it. A ſleightneſſe of ſpirit in taking this Covenant, muſt needs cauſe a ſleightneſſe of ſpirit in keeping it. All ſolemne duties ought to have ſolemne preparations, and this I thinke as ſolemne, as any. A Chriſtian ought to ſet his heart (as far as he can through the ſtrength of Chriſt) into a praying frame, before he kneels downe to prayer. And we ought to ſet our hearts in a promiſing frame, before we ſtand up to make ſuch mighty promiſes. <hi>Take heed how ye heare,</hi> is our Saviours admonition in the Goſpel; Surely then we had need <hi>take heed how we ſweare. Let a man examine himſelfe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul) and ſo let him eat of that bread and drinke of that cup;</hi> let him come examin'd to the <hi>Sacrament:</hi> ſo I may ſay, <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe before he lift up his hand or write downe his name;</hi> let him come examin'd to the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall briefly propoſe three heads of preparatory ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination reſpecting our entrance into this Covenant:</p>
            <p>Firſt, examine your hearts and your lives, whether or no you are not preingaged in any Covenant contrary to the tenour and conditions of this Covenant. If any ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155471:7"/> upon enquiry be found, be ſure you void it, before you engage your ſelves in this; A <hi>ſuper-inſtitution</hi> in this kinde is very dangerous. Every man muſt looke to it, that he takes this Covenant <hi>(ſede vacante,</hi> or rather <hi>corde vacante)</hi> with a heart emptied of all Covenants which are inconſiſtent with this. For a man to covenant with Chriſt and his people for Reformation, &amp;c. while he hath either taken a Covenant with others, or made a Covenant in his owne breaſt againſt it, is deſperate wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Or if upon a ſelfe-ſearch you finde your ſelves cleare of any ſuch ingagements, yet ſearch further. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man by nature is a <hi>Covenanter</hi> with Hell, and with every ſinne he is at <hi>Agreement:</hi> be ſure you revoke and cancell that Covenant before you ſubſcribe this. <hi>If I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not heare me pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> that is, <hi>he will not regard my prayers</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) Pſal.</hi> 66. 18. And if we regard iniquity in our hearts, the Lord will not heare us covenanting, that is, he will not regard our Covenant. Woe bee unto thoſe who make this <hi>league</hi> with God and his people, while they reſolve to continue their league with ſin: which is (upon the matter) a league with Satan. God and Satan will never meet in one Covenant. For what communion hath light with darkneſſe? and what concord hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Belial?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, before you enter into this Covenant with God, conſider of, and repent for this ſpeciall ſinne, your former breaches and failings in Gods Covenant. <hi>We who were ſometimes a far off, Aliens from the Common-wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the Covenant of promiſe, are made nigh by the blood of Jeſus,</hi> even ſo nigh as to be in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God. Some who pretend to this priviledge, will be found <hi>ſuch as have counted the blood of the Covenant</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155471:8"/> 
               <hi>to be an unholy thing, Heb.</hi> 10. 29. And where is the man that walketh ſo holily in this Covenant as becoms him, and as it requires? Labour therefore to have thoſe brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches healed by a freſh ſprinkling of the blood of Chriſt upon your conſciences, before you enter this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: If you put this new peece to an old garment, the rent will be made worſe: If you put this new wine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to old bottles, the bottles will breake, and all your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected comforts will run out and be loſt. If you ſhould not feele and ſearch your owne hearts, without doubt the Lord will, <hi>And if you be found as deceivers, you will bring a curſe upon your ſelves, and not a bleſſing</hi> (as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſpake in another caſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27. 12.) This is a Covenant of amity with God: reconciliation muſt goe before friendſhip, you can never make friendſhip till you have made peace, nor ſettle love where hoſtility is unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, enquire diligently at your owne hearts, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they come up indeed to the tearmes of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. You muſt bid high for the honour of a Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for a part in this priviledge. <hi>Which of you</hi> (ſaith our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> to his hearers, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. 28. <hi>intending to build a Tower, ſitteth not downe firſt,</hi> and counteth the coſt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he have ſufficient to finiſh it? <hi>leſt haply after he hath laid the foundation, and is not able to finiſh it, all that behold it, begin to mocke him, ſaying, This man began to build, and was not able to finiſh.</hi> We are met this day to lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of one Tower, and to pull up the foundation of another; wee are pulling up the foundation of <hi>Babels</hi> Tower, and we are laying a foundation for <hi>Sions</hi> Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. We have ſeene ſome who have heretofore done as much, but they have done no more, when they had laid a foundation for thoſe noble works in taking a ſolemne
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155471:8"/> Oath and Covenant, they have never moved a hand af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter either to build or to pull downe, unleſſe it were quite croſſe to their owne ingagements, for the pulling downe of <hi>Sions</hi> Tower, and the building of <hi>Babylone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what was the reaſon of this ſtand, or contrary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? This ſurely was one, they did not gage their own hearts before hand, neither did they ſit downe to count the coſt of ſuch an undertaking. And therefore when they perceived the charge to ariſe ſo high, they neither could finiſh, nor would they endeavour it, but left the worke before it lookt above the ground; and are juſtly become a mock, and a ſcorn, and a reproach in <hi>Iſrael, Theſe they are the men that began (in a ſolemn Covenant) to build, but could not finiſh; They had not ſtocke enough either of true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or honeſty (though their ſtocke of parts and opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties was ſufficient) to finiſh this worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore ſit downe ſeriouſly and count the coſt; yea, and conſider whether we be willing to be at the coſt. To lead you on in this, my humble advice is, That you would <hi>catechiſe</hi> your hearts upon the Articles of this Covenant. Put the queſtion to your hearts, and let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſay thus unto himſelfe:</p>
            <p>Am I indeed reſolved ſincerely, really and conſtantly, through the grace of God, in my place and calling, to endeavour the preſervation of the reformed Religion in the Church of <hi>Scotland? &amp;c.</hi> The reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Am I indeed reſolved in like manner, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, to endeavour the extirpation of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Prelacy? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Am I indeed reſolved never to be withdrawne or divided by whatſover terrour or perſwaſion from this bleſſed union and conjunction, whether to make
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155471:9"/> defection to the contrary part, or to give my ſelfe to a deteſtable indifferency or neutrality, in this cauſe of God? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Am I indeed reſolved to humble my ſelfe for my owne ſins and the ſins of the Kingdome? &amp;c. to amend my ſelfe and all in my power, and to goe before others in the example of a reall reformation? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>According to theſe hints, propoſe the queſtion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every clauſe of this Covenant. And then conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what the coſt of performing all theſe may amount to, and whether you are willing to goe to that coſt.</p>
            <p>But it may be, ſome will ſay, What is this coſt? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, The expreſſe letter of the Covenant tells you of one coſt which you muſt be conſtantly at, and that is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, reall, and conſtant endeavour. Paines is a price, I am ſure reall pains is. The Heathens ſaid, That their gods ſold them all good things for labour. The good things of this Covenant are ſold at that rate; yea, this is the price which the true God puts upon thoſe things which he freely gives. To conſent to this Covenant, to wiſh well to this Covenant, to ſpeake well of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, come not up to the price; you muſt doe theſe and you muſt doe more, you muſt be doing, ſo the promiſe of every man for himſelfe runnes, <hi>I will through the grace of God endeavour.</hi> Yet every endeavour is not cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant money, payable, as the price of this Covenant, there muſt be a threefold ſtampe upon it, unleſſe it beare the image and ſuperſcription of ſincerity, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and conſtancy, it will not be accepted. For ſo the promiſe runs, <hi>I will ſincerely, really, and conſtantly endeavour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither yet is this all, ſuch endeavours are vertually money, but this covenant cals alſo for money formally
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155471:9"/> as the price of it; He that really endeavours after ſuch ends, as here are propoſed, muſt not onely be at the coſt of his paines, but alſo at the coſt of his purſe for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement of them. He muſt open his hand to give and to lend, as well as to worke and labour; unleſſe a man be free of his Purſe, as well as of his paines, he bids not up to the demands of this Covenant, nor payes up to his owne promiſe, when he enter'd it. Can that man be ſaid really to endeavour the maintenance of a cauſe, while he lets it ſtarve? or to ſtrengthen it, whiles he keepes the ſinewes of it cloſe ſhut up? Would he have the Chariot move ſwiftly who onely drawes, but will not Oyle the Wheeles? Know then, and conſider it, that the coſt you muſt be at, is both in your labours, and in your eſtates. The engagement runnes to both theſe.</p>
            <p>And to more then both theſe, This Covenant enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges us, not onely to doe, but to ſuffer; not onely to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, but to endure. Such is the tenour of the ſixth Article, where every man promiſes for himſelfe; <hi>That he will not ſuffer himſelfe to be withdrawne from this bleſſed union, by any terrours.</hi> If not by any terrour, then not by loſſes, impriſonments, torments, no nor by death, <hi>that King of Terrour.</hi> You ſee then that the price of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, may be the price of blood, of liberty and of life. Sit downe and conſider, are you willing to be at this coſt to build the Tower? Through the goodneſſe of God in ordering theſe great affaires, you may never come actually to pay downe ſo much: haply, not halfe ſo much; but except you reſolve (if call'd and put to it by the reall exigencies of this cauſe) to pay downe the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Farthing, your Spirits are too narrow, and your hearts too low for the honour and tenour of this Covenant.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:155471:10"/>
            <p>If any ſhall ſay theſe demands are very high, and the charge very great; but is a part in this Covenant worth it? will it quit coſt to be at ſo great a charge? wiſe men love to ſee and have ſomewhat for their money; and when they ſee they will not ſticke at any coſt, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations be valuable.</p>
            <p>For the anſwering and clearing of this I ſhall paſſe to the ſecond point, which holds forth the grounds of a Covenant, from thoſe words of the text, <hi>And becauſe of all this.</hi> If any one ſhall be troubled at the <hi>All this,</hi> in the price, I doubt not but the <hi>All this</hi> in the grounds will ſatisfie him. Becauſe of <hi>All this we make a ſure Covenant.</hi> Here obſerve.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>A Covenant muſt be grounded on reaſon;</hi> We muſt ſhew cauſe why. God often deſcends, but man is bound to give a reaſon of what he doth. Some of Gods actions are above reaſon, but none without reaſon. All our actions ought to be levell with reaſon, and this with common reaſon, for it is a common act, That which men of all capacities are called to doe, ſhould lie in the reach of every mans capacity. Obſerve</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>A Covenant muſt be grounded on weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> There muſt be much light in the reaſon (as was ſhewed before) but no lightneſſe. <hi>Becauſe of all this,</hi> ſaith the Text, there were many things in it, and much weight in every one of them.</p>
            <p>And the reaſons in their proportion, muſt at leaſt be as weighty as the conditions. Weighty conditions will never be ballanced with light reaſons. If a man aske a thouſand pounds for a Iewell, he is bound to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that his Iewell is intrinſecally worth ſo much, elſe no wiſe man wil come up to his demands. So when great things are demanded to be payd down by all who take
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155471:10"/> part in this Covenant, we are obliged to demonſtrate and hold forth an equivalence of worth in the grounds and nature of it. Hence Obſerve</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That the reaſons of a Covenant muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, Becauſe of all this. This,</hi> is demonſtrative. Here's the matter laid before you, conſider of it, examine it thoroughly. This is faire dealing, when a man ſees why he undertakes, and what he may expect, before he is engaged. And ſo may ſay, becauſe of <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>this,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of <hi>all this,</hi> I have entered into Covenant.</p>
            <p>But what were the particulars that made up the <hi>groſse ſumme of all this?</hi> I anſwer, thoſe particulars lie ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red throughout the Chapter, the attentive Reader will eaſily finde them out; I ſhall in briefe reduce them unto two heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the defection and corruptions that were crept in, or openly brought in among them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the afflictions, troubles, and judgements that either were already fallen, or were feared would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fall upon them.</p>
            <p>The former of theſe cauſes is laid downe in the 34. and 35. verſes of this Chapter. <hi>Neither have our Kings, our Princes, our Prieſts, nor our fathers kept thy Law, nor hearkned to thy Commandements, and thy Teſtimonies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou didſt teſtifie againſt them. For they have not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thee in their Kingdom, and in thy great goodneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The latter of theſe reaſons is contained in the 36 and 37 verſes. <hi>Behold we are ſervants this day; and for the Land which thou gaveſt unto our fathers, to eate the fruit thereof, and the good thereof, behold we are ſervants in it, &amp;c.</hi> The cloſe of all is, <hi>We are in great diſtreſſe.</hi> From this narratiue of the grounds, the making of a Covenant is inferred as a concluſion, in the immediate ſubſequent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155471:11"/> words of the Text, <hi>Becauſe of all this.</hi> As if he had ſaid, <hi>Becauſe we are a people who have ſo departed from the Lawes and Statutes of our God, and are ſo corrupted both in worſhip and in practice; Becauſe we are a people ſo oppreſſed in our eſtates, and liberties, and ſo diſtreſſed by judgements and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions: Therefore, Becauſe of all this we make a ſure Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we peruſe the records of holy Scripture, we ſhall finde, that either both theſe grounds conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or one of them, are expreſt as the reaſons at any time inducing the people of God, to enter into the Bond of a Covenant. This is evident in <hi>Aſa's</hi> Covenant, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 15. 12, 13. In <hi>Hezekiahs,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. 10. In <hi>Ioſias,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34. 30, 31. In <hi>Ezra's,</hi> c. 10. v. 3. of that Booke. To all which I referre the reader for ſatisfaction. And from all conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with this in the Text, I Obſerve:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That when a people are corrupted or declined in doctrine, worſhip, and manners; when they are diſtreſſed in their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, livelihoods, or lives; Then, and at ſuch a time they have warrantable and ſufficient Grounds to make and engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as their laſt and higheſt reſort for redreſſe) in the bonds of a ſacred ſolemne Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What engagement can be upon us, which theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons doe not reach and anſwer? The libertie of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and of our eſtates is worth much, but the liberty of the Goſpell, the purity of Doctrine and Ordinances, are worth much more. Peace is a precious Jewell, but who can value truth? The wiſe Merchant will ſell all that he hath with joy to buy this, and bleſſes God for the bargaine, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 44.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And beeauſe of all this,</hi> we are called to make a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant this day. Truth of doctrine and purity of worſhip were going, and much of them both were gone. The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155471:11"/> liberty of our perſons, and property of our eſtates, were going, and much of them both were gone; we were at once growing <hi>popiſh and ſlaviſh, ſuperſtitious and ſervile;</hi> We were in theſe great diſtreſſes, <hi>and becauſe of all this, we make a Covenant thu day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe are the grounds of our Covenant, is cleare in the tenour of the Covenant. The preamble whereof ſpeakes thus:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>WE calling to minde the treacherous and bloody plots, conſpiracies, attempts and practices of the enemies of God, againſt the true Religion and Profeſſours thereof, in all places, eſpecially in theſe three Kingdomes ever ſince the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Religion; And how much their rage, power, and preſumption, are of late and at this time increaſed and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, whereof the deplorable eſtate of the Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of</hi> Ireland, <hi>the diſtreſſed eſtate of the Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of</hi> England, <hi>and the dangerous eſtate of the Church and Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>are preſent and publique teſtimonies. We have now at the laſt, for the preſervation of our ſelves and our Religion from utter ruine and deſtruction, &amp;c. after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation reſolved and determined to enter into a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and ſolemne League and Covenant, &amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>So then if we be askt a reaſon of our Covenant, here are reaſons, cleare reaſons, eaſie to the weakeſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, yea open to every mans ſence; who amongſt us hath not felt theſe reaſons? and how many have ſmarted their proofe unto us? And as theſe reaſons are ſo plaine, that the moſt illiterate and vulgar underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings may conceive them; ſo they are ſo weighty and cogent that the moſt ſubtile and ſublime underſtandings cannot but be ſubdued to them; unleſſe, becauſe they are ſuch maſters of reaſon, they have reſolved to obey
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155471:12"/> none. And yet where conſcience is indeed unſatisfied, we ſhould rather pity then impoſe, and labour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, rather then violently to obtrude. Now ſeeing we have <hi>all this</hi> for the ground of a Covenant, let us cheerefully and reverently make a <hi>ſure</hi> Covenant. Which is the third point in the Text, The property of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, we make <hi>a ſure Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Hebrew, the word Covenant is not expreſt. The <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Text runnes onely thus, <hi>We make a ſure one,</hi> or a ſure thing. Covenants are in their owne nature and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, things of ſo much certainty and aſſurance, that by way of excellence a Covenant is called, <hi>a ſure one, or an aſſurance.</hi> When a <hi>ſure one</hi> is but named, a <hi>Covenant</hi> muſt be underſtood. As, <hi>the Holy One</hi> is God, and <hi>the Holy One and the juſt, is Chriſt,</hi> Acts 3. 14. You may know whom the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> meanes, when he ſaith, <hi>the holy One, and the juſt.</hi> So the ſure one is a Covenant, you may know what they made when the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſaith, they made <hi>a ſure one.</hi> Hence obſerve, that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A well-grounded Covenant is a ſure, a firme, and an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable Act.</hi> When you have ſuch an <hi>all this,</hi> (and ſuch you have) as is here concenter'd in the Text, to lay into or for the foundation of a Covenant, the ſuperſtruction (is <hi>aeternitati ſacrum,</hi> and) muſt ſtand for ever.</p>
            <p>A weake ground is but a weake obligation; and a ſinfull ground is no obligation. There is much ſinne in making a Covenant upon ſinfull grounds, and there is more ſinne in keeping of it. But when the preſervation of <hi>true Religion,</hi> and the vindication of <hi>juſt Liberties</hi> meet in the ground-worke, ye may <hi>ſweare and not repent; yea, if ye ſweare, ye muſt not repent.</hi> For becauſe of all ſuch things as theſe, we ought (if we make any, and that we ought) to make a <hi>ſure Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:155471:12"/>
            <p>The Covenant which God makes with man is a <hi>ſure Covenant.</hi> Hence called a <hi>Covenant of Salt, Numb.</hi> 18. 19. Becauſe Salt preſerves from periſhing and putrifaction. The Covenant of God with man about temporall things is called a <hi>Covenant of Salt, and a Covenant for ever,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 3. For though his Covenant about temporall things (as all temporals muſt) hath an end of termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet it hath no end of corruption; time will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it, but time cannot violate it. But as for his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant about eternall things, that, like eternity knowes not onely no end of corruption, but none of terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Although my Houſe</hi> (ſaith gaſping <hi>David) be not ſo with God, yet be hath made with me an everlaſting Covenant, ordered in all things and ſure: for this is all my ſalvation and all my deſire, although he make it not to grow,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 5. And what is it that makes the Covenant of God with man thus ſure? <hi>Sure</hi> not onely in it ſelfe, but (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes) <hi>to all the ſeed, Rom</hi> 5. 16. Is it not this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath a ſtrong foundation, a double, impregnable foundation? Firſt, <hi>his owne free grace.</hi> Secondly, <hi>the blood of Cbriſt;</hi> which is therefore alſo called, <hi>the blood of the Covenant, Heb.</hi> 10. 29. Becauſe of <hi>all this,</hi> this All, which hath an infinity in it, The Lord God hath made with us a ſure Covenant.</p>
            <p>Now as the ſtability and everlaſtingneſſe of Gods Covenant with his elect, lies in the ſtrength of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, <hi>His owne love, and the blood of his Sonne.</hi> So the ſtability and firmneſſe of our Covenant with God, lies in the ſtrength of this foundation. The ſecuring of the Goſpell, and the aſſerting of Goſpell-purity in worſhip and priviledges in Government: the ſecuring of our lives, and the aſſerting of our common liberties. When at any time ye can queſtion, and (from the Oracles of truth)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155471:13"/> be reſolved, that theſe are inſufficient grounds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Covenant, or that theſe are not ours, ye may goe, and un-aſſure the Covenant which ye make this day.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore invite you in the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <note place="margin">Application.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremy,</hi> chap. 50. 5. <hi>Come let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall Covenant, that ſhall never be forgotten.</hi> And doe not theſe looke like the daies wherein the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet cals to the doing of this? <hi>In thoſe daies, and at that time, ſaith the Lord,</hi> verſ. 4. What time and what daies were thoſe? The beginning of the Chapter anſwers it. <hi>The word that the Lord ſpake againſt Babylon, &amp;c. declare ye among the Nations, and publiſh and ſet up a Standard, publiſh and conceale not: ſay, Babylon is taken, Bel is confounded, Merodach is broken in pieces; her Idols are confounded, her Images are broken in pieces: For out of the North there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth up a Nation againſt her, which ſhall make her Land deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, &amp;c.</hi> Then followes, <hi>in thoſe daies and at that time, ſaith the Lord, the children of Iſrael ſhall come, &amp;c. And they ſhall aske the way to Zion, with their faces thitherward, ſaying, Come and let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not theſe the daies, and this the time (I ſpeake not of time to a day, but of time and daies) wherein the Lord ſpeakes againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> and againſt the Land of the <hi>Chaldeans?</hi> Wherein he ſaith, declare among the Nations, and publiſh, and ſet up the Standard; Are not theſe the daies, and this the time when out of the North there commeth up a Nation againſt her? As face an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers face in the water, ſo doe the events of theſe daies anſwer, if not the Letter, yet much of the myſtery of this prophecy. There ſeemes wanting onely the worke which this day is bringing forth, and a few daies more (I hope) will bring unto perfection, the joyning of our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155471:13"/> ſelves in a perpetuall Covenant never to be forgotten. It is very obſervable how the Prophet as it were with one breath ſaith, <hi>Babylon is taken</hi> (verſ. 2.) and <hi>come let us joyne our ſelves in Covenant,</hi> verſ. 5. as if there were no more in it but this, <hi>Take the Covenant, and ye take Babylon.</hi> Or, as if the taking of a Covenant were the ready way, the readieſt way to take <hi>Babylon.</hi> Surely at the report of the taking of this <hi>ſure Covenant,</hi> we in our prayer-viſions (as the Prophet <hi>Habakkuc</hi> in his c. 3. v. 7.) <hi>may ſee the tents of Cuſhan in affliction, and the curtaines of the Land of Midian tremble.</hi> Or as <hi>Moſes</hi> in his triumphant ſong, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 14. <hi>The people ſhall heare and be afraid ſorrow ſhall take hold of the inhabitants of Paleſtina. The Dukes of Edom ſhall be amazed, the mighty men of Moab trembling ſhal take hold upon them, the inhabitants of Canaan</hi> (who are now the inhabitants of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon) ſhall melt away.</hi> The Towers of <hi>Babylon</hi> will quake and her <hi>ſeven hils</hi> will move. <hi>The great mountaine before our Zerubbabels will become a plaine, and we ſhall bring forth the head Stone</hi> (of our Reformation) <hi>with ſhouting, crying grace, grace unto it. Zach.</hi> 4. 7. why may we not promiſe to our ſelves ſuch glorious effects (and not build theſe Caſtles in the ayre) when we have laid ſo promiſing a foundation, <hi>this ſure Covenant, and have made a perpetuall Covenant, never to be forgotten?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three things I ſhall propoſe, which this Couenant will bring in, as facilitating contributions to ſo great a worke:</p>
            <p>Firſt, this Covenant will diſtinguiſh men, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the precious from the vile. In the twentieth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> the Lord promiſeth his people, after this manner, <hi>I will cauſe you to paſſe under the rod, and I will bring you into the bond of the Covenant,</hi> verſ. 37. That phraſe of <hi>cauſing to paſſe under the rod</hi> is an alluſion to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155471:14"/> ſhepheards, or the keepers of Cattell, who when they would take ſpeciall notice of their Sheepe or Cattell, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their number to tithe them, or in their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to try them, they brought them into a Fold, or ſome other encloſed place, where letting them paſſe out at a narrow doore one by one, they held a rod over them to count or conſider more diſtinctly of them. This action was called a <hi>paſſing of them under the rod,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> teacheth us, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27. 32. <hi>And concerning the tithe of the heard, or of the flocke, even of whatſoever paſſeth under the rod, the tenth ſhall be holy unto the Lord.</hi> The learned <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Totum populum Iſraelis, ita pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babo &amp; recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcam, ut pastor gregem; ad reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendos in faedus &amp; in caulam meam bonos, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proboſque abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candos. Jun. in in Loc.</note> expounds that Text in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> by this in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> giving the ſence thus, as if the Lord had ſaid, I will prove and try the whole people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as a ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard doth his flocke, that I may take the good and ſound into the Fold of my Covenant, and caſt out the wicked and unſound; which interpretation is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favoured but fully approved, in the words immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately following, verſ. 38. <hi>I will bring you into the bond of the Covenant, and I will purge out from among you the rebels and them that tranſgreſſe againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Covenant is to a Nation as a Fan to the Floore, which purges away the Chaffe, and purifies the Wheate. It is like the Furnace to the Mettall, which takes away the droſſe, and ſhewes you a refined lumpe. It is a <hi>Shibboleth</hi> to diſtinguiſh Ephraimites from Gileadites, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 12. 6. And who knowes not how great an advantage it is for the ſucceſſefull carrying on of any honourable deſigne, to know friends from enemies, and the faithfull from falſe brethren? ſome have thought it unpoliticall to ſet a foote this Covenant, leſt it ſhould diſcover more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies then friends, and ſo holding out to the view, more then otherwiſe can be ſeene, the weakeneſſe of a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155471:14"/> party may render them, not onely more obnoxious, but more inconſiderable.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer in a word, Inviſible enemies will ever doe us more hurt then viſible; and if wee cannot deliver our ſelves from them when they are ſeene and knowne, doubtleſſe unſeene and unknowne they will more eaſily, though more inſenſibly devoure us. And I verily beleeve, we have already received more dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and deeper wounds from pretended friends, then from profeſt and open enemies. The ſad ſtories of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> and <hi>Amaſa</hi> informe us, That there is no ſence againſt his ſtroke who comes too neere us, who ſtabs while he <hi>takes us aſide to ſpeake kindely to us,</hi> who drawes his ſword while he hath a kiſſe at his lips, <hi>and art thou in health my brother,</hi> at his tongue. Let us never thinke our ſelves ſtronger becauſe we doe not know our weakneſſe, or ſafer becauſe we are ignorant of our danger. Or that our reall enemies and falſe friends will doe us leſſe hurt, becauſe they are leſſe diſcovered. I doe not thinke that a flocke ever fared the better, becauſe the Wolves that were amongſt them went in ſheeps clothing. Rather will our knowledge be our ſecurity, and the diſcovery which this Covenant makes, helpe on both our deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and our buſineſſe. For as (poſſibly) this Covenant may diſcover thoſe who are faithfull to be fewer then was ſuppoſed before this ſtrict diſtinction from others, ſo it will certainly make them ſtronger then they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by a ſtricter union among themſelves. And this is</p>
            <p>The ſecond benefit of this Covenant, which I ſhall next inſiſt upon. As it doth ſeparate thoſe who are he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneall, ſo likewiſe it will congregate and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body thoſe who are homogeneall. And therefore it cannot but adde ſtrength unto a people; <hi>for whatſoever</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:155471:15"/> 
               <hi>unites, ſtrengthens.</hi> A few united are ſtronger then a ſcattered multitude. Though they who ſubſcribe this Covenant ſhould be (comparatively) ſo few (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeakes, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 10. 19. <hi>that a childe may write them;</hi> yet this few thus united are ſtronger then ſo many ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd ones (as exceed all <hi>Arithmeticke)</hi> whom (as <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. 9. <hi>no man can number. Cloven tongues were ſent (Acts</hi> 2. 3.) to publiſh the Goſpell, but not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided tongues, much leſſe divided hearts: The former mer hindred the building of <hi>Babel, Gen.</hi> 11. 7.) and the latter (though tongues ſhould agree) will hinder the building of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Then a worke goes on amaine when the undertakers (whether they be few or many) <hi>ſpeake all and thinke the ſame thing.</hi> A people are more conſiderable in any worke, becauſe they are <hi>One,</hi> then becauſe they are <hi>Many.</hi> But when <hi>many and one</hi> meete, nothing can ſtand before them. So the Lord God obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when <hi>he came down to ſee the City and the Tower which the children of men builded,</hi> Gen. 11. 5. <hi>And the Lord ſaid</hi> (at the ſixth verſe) <hi>behold the people is One, and they have all One language: And this they begin to doe; and now nothing will be reſtrained from them, which they have imagined to doe.</hi> Men may doe as much as they can thinke, while they <hi>All</hi> thinke and doe as one; and not onely can ſuch doe great things, if let alone; but none can let them in doing what they intend; ſo ſaith the Lord in <hi>Geneſis, They have begunne to doe, and nothing will be reſtrained from them which they have imagined.</hi> Nothing could reſtraine or let them from their worke, but his power who will <hi>worke and none can let it,</hi> Iſa. 43. 13.</p>
            <p>Thus it is apparent that union is our ſtrength, and it is as apparent, That this Covenant (through the bleſſing of God upon it) will be our union. To unite is the very
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155471:15"/> nature of a Covenant. Hence <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 37. It is called the <hi>bond of the Covenant, I will bring you into the bond of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Maſoreth &amp; Maſora, traditie, dectrina per me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus à majoribus tradita, &amp; ſine literis ad poſteras tranſmiſſa Schind.</hi>
               </note> ſaith the Lord. <hi>Iunius</hi> and ſome others render it, <hi>I will bring you (ad exhibitionem faederis) to the giving or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Covenant:</hi> Deriving the word from <hi>Maſar,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying, to exhibite or deliver. Whence (to note that in paſſage) the Traditionary doctrine among the Jewes, is called <hi>Maſora</hi> or <hi>Maſoreth.</hi> Others (whom our Tranſlators follow, and put the former ſence, <hi>delivering,</hi> in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.) Others (I ſay) deriving the word from <hi>Aſar</hi> to bind, render it the <hi>bond of the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Covenant is the <hi>bond</hi> of a twofold union. Firſt, it unites us of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> among our ſelves, and this <hi>Kingdome</hi> with the other two. Secondly, it makes a ſpeciall union of all thoſe, who ſhall take it holily and ſincerely throughout the three Kingdomes, with the One-moſt God. Weake things bound together are ſtrong, much more then, when ſtrong are bound up with ſtrong; moſt of all, when ſtrong are bound up with Almighty. If in this Covenant we ſhould onely joyne weake to weake, we might be ſtrong. But (bleſſed be God) we joyne ſtrong (as creatures may be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſtrong) with ſtrong. The ſtrong Kingdomes of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the ſtrong Kingdome of <hi>Scotland.</hi> A <hi>threefold coard</hi> twiſted of three ſuch ſtrong Coards will not eaſily, if at all, be broken. They which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle (bleſſed be God) have yet ſuch ſtrength, how ſtrong may they be when conjoyned? As the Apoſtle writes to his Romans (c. 6. 19.) <hi>I ſpeake after the manner of men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the infirmity of our fleſh:</hi> So I ſpeake now after the manner of men, concerning the ſtrength of our fleſh (outward meanes) in theſe Kingdomes. For as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes in like phraſe, though to another occaſion, (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>the Lord is not ſlack concerning his</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:155471:16"/> 
               <hi>promiſe, as ſome men count ſlackneſſe.</hi> So I may ſay, no man, no Kingdomes are ſtrong to any purpoſe, as the <hi>Lord counts ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I reckon this the leaſt part of our ſtrength, that theſe three ſtrong Kingdomes will be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by this Covenant; nay, if this were all the ſtrength which this union were like to make, I ſhould reckon this no ſtrength at all; wherfore know that this covenant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is and will be a bond of union between <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>Almighty:</hi> betweene <hi>three ſtrong Nations,</hi> and an <hi>Almighty God.</hi> This Covenant engages more then <hi>Man, God</hi> alſo is engaged; engaged (through his free grace) in his <hi>power, wiſdome faithfulneſſe,</hi> to do as good and much good, though in and of our ſelves unworthy of the leaſt, unworthy of my good.</p>
            <p>All this conſidered, this Covenant wil be our ſtrength, our brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> have (in a plentifull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) found it ſo already. This Covenant (through the bleſſing of God upon their counſels and endeavours) hath beene their <hi>Sampſons Locke,</hi> the thing (in fight) wherein their ſtrength lieth. And why ſhould not we hope, that it will be ours; if we can be wiſe, as they, to prevent or overcome the flattering enticements of thoſe <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> who would lull us aſleepe in their <hi>laps,</hi> onely for an opportunity to cut or <hi>ſhave it off?</hi> Then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (which God forbid) we ſhould be but weake, like other men, yea weaker then our ſelves were before this Locke was growne, having but the ſtrength of man; God utterly departing from us, for our falſeneſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe in this Covenant.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this Covenant obſerved, will make us an <hi>holy people,</hi> and then, we cannot be an <hi>unhappy people.</hi> That which promotes perſonall holineſſe, muſt needs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Nationall holineſſe. The conſideration that we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155471:16"/> are in the bonds of a Covenant, is both a bridle to ſtop us from ſinne, and a ſpurre to duty. When we provoke God to bring evill upon us, he ſtayes his hand by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering his Covenant. <hi>I will remember my Covenant (ſaith the Lord,</hi> Gen. 9. 15.) <hi>which is betweene me and you, and every living creature of all fleſh; and the waters ſhall no more become a flood to deſtroy all fleſh.</hi> As if the <hi>Lord</hi> had ſaid, It is more then probable that I ſhall quickly ſee as much cauſe <hi>(all fleſh corrupting all their wayes before me)</hi> to drowne the world with a ſecond deluge, as I did for the firſt: the foulneſſe of the world will quickly call for another waſhing. But I am reſolved never to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it by water againe, for, <hi>I will remember my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> Hence alſo in the ſecond booke of the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>chap.</hi> 21. where the reigne and ſinnes of <hi>Jehoram</hi> are recorded, ſuch ſinnes as might juſtly put a ſword into the hand of God to cut him off <hi>root and branch, Howbeit</hi> (ſaith the Text, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.) <hi>the Lord would not deſtroy the houſe of David, becauſe of the Covenant that he had made with David, and as he promiſed to give a light to him, &amp; to his ſons for ever.</hi> Now as the remembrance of the Covenant on his part ſtayes the hand of God from ſmiting, ſo the remembrance of the Covenant on our part, will be very effectuall to ſtay our hands, and tongues, and hearts from ſinning. A thought of that will dampe and ſilence our luſts and paſſions, when they begin to move or queſt within us, it will alſo breake the blow of Satans temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations when hee aſſaults us. The ſoule in ſuch caſes will anſwer, True! I am now as ſtrongly tempted to ſinne as ever, I have now as faire an opportunity to commit this ſinne as ever, I could now be falſe to, and deſert this cauſe with as much advantage, upon as faire hopes, and promiſes as ever: O but I am in Covenant, I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155471:17"/> remember my Covenant, I will not, I cannot doe it; and ſo he falls a praying againſt the temptation; yea, he begs prayers of others, that he may be ſtrengthned againſt and overcome it. I read you an inſtance of this effect before the Sermon, a paper is ſent to this congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation containing this requeſt: <hi>One who through much paſſion oftentimes grievouſly offends the Majeſty of God by curſing and ſwearing, and that ſince his late taking the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, deſires the prayers of this Congregation that his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence may be pardoned, and that he may be enabled to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come that temptation from hence forwards.</hi> This is the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that requeſt to a letter and a tittle, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſee, how the remembrance of the Covenant wrought. Probably this party (whoſoever he was) took little notice of, or was little troubled at the notice of theſe diſtempers in himſelfe before, leaſt of all ſought out for helpe againſt them. And I have the rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted this to confute that ſcorne which I heare) ſome have ſince put upon that conſcientious deſire. As if one had complained, that ſince his ſwearing to the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> he could not forbeare ſwearing, and that this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oath had taught him prophane ones. But what <hi>holy thing</hi> is there, which <hi>ſwine</hi> will not make mire of, for themſelves to wallow in? I returne, and I nothing doubt but that this Covenant (wherein all is undertaken through the grace of Chriſt) will make many more gracious who had grace before, and turne others who were running on amain in the broad way, from the evill and errour of their wayes, into the way which is called Holy, or into the wayes of Holineſſe. Every Act wherein we converſe with an holy God, hath an influence upon our ſpirits to make us holy. The ſoule is made more holy in prayer, though holineſſe be not the particular matter
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155471:17"/> of the prayer; A man gets much of Heaven into his heart, in praying for earthly things, if he pray in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall manner; And the reaſon is, becauſe in prayer he hath converſe with, and drawes nigh to God, whatſoever lawfull thing he prayes about. And the ſame reaſon caries it in covenanting, though it were only about the maintenance of our outward Eſtates and liberties, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as therein we have to doe with God. How much more then will holineſſe be encreaſed through <hi>this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> which in many branches of it, is a direct Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for and about holineſſe? And if we improve it home to this purpoſe for the ſubduing of thoſe myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Canaanites,</hi> thoſe worſt and (indeed) moſt formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemies, our ſinfull luſts, if we improve it for the obtaining of more grace, and the making of us more holy: though our viſible <hi>Caananites</hi> ſhould not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue unſubdued by us, but ſubdue us, Though our Eſtates and Liberties ſhould continue, not only unreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but quite loſt, though we ſhould neither bee a rich, nor a free, nor a victorious people, yet if we are an <hi>holy people,</hi> we have more then <hi>All theſe,</hi> we have <hi>all,</hi> he is ours, <hi>who is All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much of the firſt generall part of the application.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is for Admonition and Caution in three or foure particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, take heed of <hi>prophaning this Covenant, Mal.</hi> 2. 8. by an unholy life. Remember you have made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Heaven; then doe not live as if you had <hi>made a Covenant with Hell, or were come to an agreement with Death,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> characters thoſe monſters of prophaneſſe, <hi>c.</hi> 28. 15. Take heede alſo of <hi>corrupting this Covenant, Mal.</hi> 2. 10. by an unholy gloſſe. Woe be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe gloſſes that corrupt the Text, pervert the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:155471:18"/> of theſe words: Who attempt to expound the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant by their own practice, and will not regulate their practice by the Covenant. <hi>The Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Pauls</hi> writings, <hi>that in them ſome things are hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable, wreſt, as they doe alſo the other Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</hi> 2 Epiſt. c. 3. v. 16. We may feare that though the Text of this Covenant be <hi>eaſy to be underſtood,</hi> yet ſome (who, at leaſt thinke themſelves) <hi>learned,</hi> And whom wee have found not onely ſtable but ſtiffened in their owne erroneous principles and opinions, will bee trying their skill (if not their malice) to wreſt, or (as the Greeke imports) to torture and ſet this Covenant upon <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the Rack, to make it ſpeake and confeſſe a ſence never intended by the compoſers, or propoſers of it: and whereof (if but common ingenuity be the Judge) it never will, nor can be found guilty. All that I ſhall ſay to ſuch, is that in cloſe of the verſe quoted from the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> let them take heed ſuch <hi>wreſtings</hi> be not (worſt to themſelves, even) <hi>to their owne deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, take heed of <hi>delaying</hi> to performe the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Covenant; ſome (I feare) who have made haſte to take the Covenant, will take leyſure to act it. It is poſſible, that a man may make too much haſte (when hee ſweares, before he conſiders what it is) to take an Oath; But having taken, it (upon due conſideration) he cannot make too much haſte to performe it, <hi>Benot raſh with thy mouth</hi> (Sayth the Preacher, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 2.) That is, doe not vow raſhly, but (v 4) <hi>when thou voweſt a vow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, deferre not to pay it, for he hath no pleaſure in fooles</hi> (Slow performance is folly) <hi>pay that which thou haſt vowed.</hi> Speedy paying (like ſpeedy giving) is double payment; whereas ſlow payment is no payment, or as
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155471:18"/> bad as none, for it is fooliſh payment. A bond (if I miſtake not) is preſently due in Law, if no day be ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed in the Bond, It is ſo I am ſure in this Covenant, here is no day ſet downe, and therefore all is due the ſame day you take it; God and man may ſue this Bond preſently for non payment; The Covenant gives no day, and therefore requires the next day, every day. It is not ſafe to take day for payment, when (the <hi>obligation is interminis de praeſenti,</hi> and) none is given.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, take heed of <hi>dallying</hi> with this Covenant; It is more then ſerious, a ſacred Covenant: it is very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous jeſting with edge tooles; this Covenant is as keen as it is ſtrong. Doe not play faſt and looſe with it, be not in and out with it, <hi>God is an avenger of all ſuch, he is a jealous God, and will not hold them guiltleſſe who thus take his name in vaine.</hi> They who <hi>ſweare by or to the Lord, and ſweare by Malcham are threatned to be cut off.</hi> Zeph. 1. 5. To be on both ſides, and to be on no ſide; neutrality and indifferency differ little, either in their ſinne or danger.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, above all take heed of Apoſtatizing from, or an utter deſertion of this Covenant. To be deſerted of God is the greateſt puniſhment, and to deſert God is the greateſt ſinne. When you have ſet your hands to the plough, doe not looke back, <hi>Remember Lots Wife.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſinne, this is, firſt, extreamely baſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honorable; It is one of the brands ſet upon thoſe <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> whom <hi>God had given up to a reprobate minde, and to vile affections</hi> (Rom. 1. 26. 28.) That they were <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant breakers.</hi> And how baſe is that iſſue which is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten betweene and borne from <hi>vile affections and a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate mind?</hi> Where the parents are ſuch, it is eaſy to judge what the child muſt be. Secondly, beſides the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155471:19"/> ſinne and the diſhonour this is extreamely dangerous and deſtructive. We are ſaid in the native ſpeaking to cut a Covenant or to ſtrike a Covenant, when we make it; And if we breake the Covenant when wee have made it, it will both ſtrike and cut us, it will kill and ſlay us. If the cords of this Covenant doe not bind us, the coards of this Covenant will whip us: and whip us, not as with <hi>Coards</hi> but as with <hi>Scorpions.</hi> The Covenant will have a quarrell with, and ſends out a challenge unto ſuch breakers of it, for reparation. And (if I may ſo ſpeake) <hi>the great God will be its ſecond.</hi> As God revenges the <hi>quarrell</hi> of his owne Covenant, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the quarrell of ours. He hath already <hi>ſent a Sword to revenge the quarrell of his Covenant,</hi> Levit. 26. 25. He will ſend another to revenge the quarrell of this upon the wilfull violatours of it. Yea every lawfull Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant hath a curſe alwayes wayting upon it, like a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall or a Sergeant to attach ſuch high contemners of it. It was noted before, from the ceremony of killing, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding and paſſing betweene the divided parts of a beaſt, when Covenants were made, that the imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a curſe upon the Covenanters was implyed, in caſe they wilfully tranſgreſſed or revolted from it. Let the Tranſgreſſors of and Revolters from this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant feare and tremble at the ſame curſe, even the curſe of a <hi>dreadfull diviſion. That God will divide them and their poſterity in</hi> Iacob <hi>and ſcatter them in our Jſrael, yea, let them feare. That God, will rebuke them, &amp; they ſhall flee farre off, and ſhall be chaſed as the chaffe of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines before the wind, and like a rolling thing before the whirlewind, This is</hi> (their portion and) <hi>the portion of them that ſpoyle us, and the Lot of them that rob us</hi> (Iſa. 17. 13, 14. And if ſo, is not their lot fallen in an unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155471:19"/> place have they not a dreadfull heritage? To be under any curſe is miſery enough, but to be under a Covenant curſe is the greateſt, is all miſery. For as the bleſſings we receive are moſt ſweete when they paſſe to us through the hands of a Covenant (a mercy from a promiſe is far better then a mercy from bare provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence becauſe then it is ſprinkl'd with the blood of Chriſt) ſo on the other ſide, the curſe which falls upon anyone is far more bitter, when it comes through a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, eſpecially an abuſed a broken Covenant. When the fiery beames of Gods wrath are contracted into this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Glaſſe, it will burne as low as Hell, and none can quench it; That alone which quenches the fire of Gods wrath, is the <hi>Blood of Chriſt.</hi> And the <hi>Blood of Chriſt</hi> is the foundation of this Covenant; Not onely is that Covenant which God hath made with us, founded in the Blood of Chriſt, but that alſo which we make with God. Were it not by the blood of Chriſt, we could not poſſibly be admitted to ſo high a priviledge. Seeing then the blood of Chriſt onely quenches the wrath of God, and this blood is the foundation of our Covenant, how ſhall the wrath of God (except they repent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and renew their Covenant) be quenched towards ſuch violators of it? And as our Saviour ſpeakes <hi>(Mat.</hi> 6.) upon another occaſion, <hi>if the light, which is in us, be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, how great is that darkeneſſe?</hi> So, I ſay, if that which is our friend turne upon us as an Enemy, how great is that enmity, and if that which is our mercy be turned into wrath, how great is that wrath, and who can quench it? It is ſayd of good <hi>King Joſiah</hi> 2 Chron. 34. 32. That when he had <hi>made a Covenant before the Lord, he cauſed all that were preſent in Ieruſalem and in Benjamin to ſtand to it.</hi> How far he interpoſed his regall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155471:20"/> I ſtay nor to diſpute. But he cauſed them to ſtand to it, that is, openly to atteſt and to maintaine it. Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes the conſideration of theſe things, ſhould reigne over the hearts of men and command in their ſpirits, more then any Prince can over the tongues or bodies of men, to cauſe them <hi>to ſtand to this Covenant.</hi> Yee, that have taken this Covenant, <hi>unleſſe yee ſtand to it, yee will fall by it.</hi> I ſhall ſhut up this point with that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>take unto you the whole Armour of God, that you may be able to withſtand in the evill day, and, when yee have done all, to ſtand.</hi> Eph. 6. 13. <hi>Stand, and withſtand.</hi> Are the <hi>watch-word</hi> of this Covenant, or the <hi>impreſſe</hi> of every heart which hath or ſhall ſincerely ſweare unto it.</p>
            <p>For the helping of you to ſtand to this Covenant I ſhall caſt in a few advices about your walking in this Covenant, or your carriage in it, which if followed, I dare ſay (through the mercy of the moſt high) your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, theſe Kingdomes, and this cauſe ſhall not miſcarry.</p>
            <p>Firſt, walke in holineſſe and uprightneſſe. When God renewed his Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> he makes this the preamble of it, <hi>I am the Almighty God, walke before me and be thou perfect, And I will make my Covenant bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene me and thee.</hi> Gen. 17. 1. 2. As this muſt be a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Salt,</hi> in regard of faithfullneſſe, ſo there muſt be ſalt in this Covenant, even the ſalt of holineſſe and uprightneſſe. The <hi>Iewes</hi> were commanded in all their offerings to uſe ſalt; and that is called the ſalt of the Covenant (Levit. 2. 13.) <hi>Every oblation of thy meate of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſhalt thou ſeaſon with Salt, neither ſhalt thou ſuffer the Salt of the Covenant of thy God to be lacking, &amp;c.</hi> What is meant by Salt on our parts, is taught us by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Marke</hi> 9. 50. <hi>Have Salt in your ſelves and have peace one with another.</hi> Which I take to be parallel in ſence
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155471:20"/> with that of the Apoſtle (Heb. 12. 14.) <hi>follow peace with all men and holineſſe, &amp;c.</hi> As Salt, the ſhadow of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, was called for, in all thoſe <hi>Iewiſh</hi> ſervices, ſo holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the true ſubſtantiall Salt, is called for in all ours. As then it was charged, <hi>Let not the Salt of the Covenant of thy God be lacking:</hi> ſo now it is charged, ſuffer not the Salt of thy Covenant with God and his people to be lacking. Seeing we have made a <hi>Covenant of ſalt,</hi> that is, a <hi>ſure Covenant</hi> let us remember to keepe ſalt in our Covenant. Let us adde ſalt to ſalt, our ſalt to the <hi>Lords Salt,</hi> our ſalt of holineſſe to his <hi>Salt of faithfulneſſe,</hi> and we ſhall not miſcarry.</p>
            <p>Secondly, walke ſteddily or ſtedfaſtly in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Where the heart is upright and holy, the feete will be ſteddy. Unſtedfaſtneſſe is a ſure argument of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundneſſe, as well as a fruit of it. <hi>Their heart was not right with him, neither were they ſtedfaſt in his Covenant,</hi> Pſal. 78. 37. As if he had ſayd, would you know the reaſon why this people were ſo unſtedfaſt? it was, becauſe they were ſo unſound. <hi>Their heart was not right with him,</hi> We often ſee the Diſeaſes of mens hearts breaking forth at their lips, and at their fingers ends, in all they ſay, or doe.</p>
            <p>Then, be hearty, and be ſteddy. God will be ſteddy to us, why ſhould not we reſolve to be ſo to him? And this Covenant will be ſtedfaſt and uniforme unto us, why ſhould not we reſolve to be ſo, to, and in this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. The Covenant will not be our friend to day and our Enemy to morrow, doe us good to day and hurt to morrow, it will not be fruitfull this yeere and barren the next; But it is our friend, to doe us good to day and ever. It is fruitfull and will be ſo for ever. Wee neede not let it ly fallow, we cannot take out the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155471:21"/> we need not let it ly fallow, we cannot take out the heart of it, though we ſhould have occaſion to plough it and ſow it every yeere. Much leſſe will this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant be ſo unſtedfaſt to its own principles, as to yield us Wheate to day and cockle to morrow, an Egge to day and to morrow a Scorpion, now Bread and anon a ſtone, now give us an embrace, and anon a wound, Now helpe on our peace, and anonne embroyle us; Now proſper our Reformation, and anon oppoſe, or hinder it; ſtrengthen us this yeere, and weaken us the next. No, as it will never be barren, ſo it will ever bring forth the ſame fruit, and that good fruit, and the more and the longer we uſe it; the better fruit; like the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Wife Prov. 31. 12. <hi>It will doe us good and not evill, all the dayes of its life.</hi> It is therefore not only ſinfull, but moſt unſutable and un-ingenuous, for us to be up and downe, forward and backward, likeing and diſliking, like that <hi>Double-minded man</hi> (Jam. 1. 8.) <hi>unſtable in all our wayes,</hi> reſpecting the duties of this Covenant.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>walke believingly,</hi> live much in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Faith. As we have no more good out of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God, then we have Faith in it, ſo no more good out of our owne, then (in a due ſence) we have faith in it. There is as much need of Faith, to improve this Covenant, as there is of faithfulneſſe. We live no more in the Sphear of a Covenant, then we believe. And we can make no living out of it but by believing. All our earnings come in (here alſo) more by our Faith, then by our workes. Let not the heart of God be ſtraitned, and his hand ſhortned by our unbeliefe. Where <hi>Chriſt</hi> marveyled at the unbelief of a people, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what a mervaile followed, omnipotence was as one weeke he could doe no mighty workes among them for them <hi>(Mar.</hi> 6. 5. 6.) works leſſe then mighty, wil not reach
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155471:21"/> our deliverances or procure our mercies. The ancient worthies made more uſe of their Faith then to be ſaved and get to Heaven by it. <hi>By Faith the walls of an oppoſing Jericho fell down</hi> (Heb 11. 30.) <hi>By Faith they ſubdued</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exercurrunt Juſtitiam, Beza.</note> 
               <hi>Kingdomes wrought righteouſneſſe,</hi> (or exerciſed Juſtice) <hi>ſtopped the mouthes of Lyons</hi> v. 33. <hi>By Faith they quenched the violence of fire, eſcaped the edge of the Sword, out of weakeneſſe they were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in fight, turned to fight the Armies of the Aliens</hi> v. 34. We have Jericho's to reduce, and Kingdomes to ſubdue, under the Scepter and government of Jeſus Chriſt, we have Juſtice to execute, and the mouthes of Lyons to ſtop, we have a violent fire to quench, A ſharpe-edged Sword to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, popiſh alien-Armies to fight with, and wee (comparatively to theſe mighty workes) are but weak; How then ſhall we out of our weakeneſſe become ſtrong, ſtrong enough to carry us thorough theſe mighty works, ſtrong enough to eſcape theſe viſible dangers, if we walke and worke by ſence and not by Fayth? And if we could get through all theſe workes and dangers without Faith, we ſhould worke but like men, not at all like Chriſtians, but like men in a politick combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not in a <hi>holy Covenant.</hi> Ther's not a ſtroke of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-worke (purely ſo called) can be done without Faith. As fire is to the Chymicke; ſo is Faith to a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-people, in that capacity they can doe nothing for themſelves without it, and they have, they can have no aſſurance, that God will. Seing then we are in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, we muſt goe to counſell by Faith, and to war by Faith, we muſt pull downe by Faith, and build by Faith, we muſt reforme by Faith and ſettle our peace by Faith. Beſides, to doe a worke ſo ſolemne and ſacred, and then to believe and expect no fruite, yea then not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155471:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:155471:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:155471:23"/> to believe and expect anſwerable fruit, is a direct <hi>tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Gods Name in vaine, and a mock to Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And if we <hi>mock Chriſt</hi> by calling him to a Covenant, which we our ſelves ſlight, as a thing we expect little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from: <hi>he will laugh at our calamity and mock when our feare commeth,</hi> Prov. 1. 26. Wherefore to cloſe, <hi>If yee will not believe, ſurely yee ſhall not be eſtabliſhed,</hi> (Iſ. 7. 9.) no, not by this <hi>ſure Covenant.</hi> But, <hi>believe in the Lord your God</hi> (in Covenant) <hi>ſo ſhall you be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, believe his Prophets, ſo ſhall you proſper,</hi> 2 Chron. 20. 20.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, walke cheerefully So it becomes thoſe that have God ſo neere them. Such, even in their ſorrowes ſhould be (like <hi>Paul</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 10) <hi>as ſorrowfull, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rejoycing.</hi> The <hi>(as)</hi> notes not a counterfeiting of ſorrow, but the overcomming of ſorrow; on this ground <hi>David</hi> reſolves againſt the feare of evill, though hee ſhould ſee nothing but evill; <hi>Though I walke in the valley of the ſhadow of Death, I will feare no evill: for thou art with me,</hi> Pſal. 23. 3. In a Covenant God and man meete, He is with us, who is more then all that are againſt us: And when he is with us, who can be againſt us? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. for then all things and all things and all perſons, even while (to the utmoſt of their skill and power) they ſet themſelves againſt us, worke for us; And ſhould we not rejoyce? If wee knew that every loſſe were our gaine, every wound our healing, every diſappoyntment our ſucceſſe, every defeate our victory, would we not rejoyce? Doe but know what it is to be in Covenant with God; and be ſad, be hopeleſſe if you can. It is to have the ſtrength and counſels of Heaven engaged for you; it is to have him for you, <hi>whoſe fooliſhneſſe is wiſer then men, and whoſe weakeneſſe is ſtronger then men,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 25.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:155471:23"/> It is to have him with you, <hi>who doth according to his will in the Army of Heaven, and amongſt the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Earth and none can stay his Hand, or ſay unto him, what doeſt thou?</hi> Daniel 4. 34. It is to have him with you, <hi>who fruſtrateth the tokens of the Lyers, and maketh the Diviners mad, who turneth wiſe men backward and maketh their knowledge fooliſh,</hi> Iſaiah 44. 25. It is to have him with you, before whom the Nations are as the droppe of a Bucket, and as the duſt of the ballance, who taketh up the Iſles as a very little thing (Iſaiah 40. 15.) In a word it is to have him with you, <hi>Who fainteth not neither is weary, there is no ſearching of his underſtanding, hee giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might, hee encreaſeth ſtrength,</hi> Verſe 28. 29. This God is our God, our God in Covenant, This is our Beloved, and this is our friend, O Daughters of Jeruſalem. And ſhall wee not rejoyce? Shall wee not walke cheerfully? Though there bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but trouble before our Eyes, yet our hearts ſhould live in thoſe upper Regions, which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Stormes and Tempeſts, above Raine and Windes, above the noyſe and confuſions of the World. Why ſhould ſorrow ſit clouded in our Faces, or any darkeneſſe be in our hearts, while wee are in the ſhine and light of Gods Countenance.? It is ſayd (2 Chro. 15. 15.) <hi>That all Judah rejoyced at the Oath. For they had ſworne with all their Heart;</hi> If we have ſworne heartily, we ſhall rejoyce heartily. And for ever baniſh baſe feares, and killing ſorrowes from our hearts, and wipe them from our faces. They, who have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy feares in their hearts, give too faire an evidence, that they did not ſweare with their hearts.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:155471:24"/>
            <p>Fiftly, walke humbly and dependantly; rejoyce, but bee not ſecure. Truſt to God in Covenant, not to your Covenant. Make not your Covenant, your Chriſt; no, not for this Temporall Salvation. As a Horſe truſted to, is a vaine thing to ſave a man, Pſal. 32. ſo likewiſe is a Covenant truſted to; neither can it deliver a Nation by its great ſtrength: though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ſtrength of it bee greater, then the ſtrength of many Horſes. In vaine is ſalvation ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for from this Hill, or from a multiude of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines heaped up and joyned in one by the bond of this Covenant. Surely in the Lord our God, our God, in Covenant, is the Salvation of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> Wee cannot truſt too much in GOD, nor too little in the Creature; There is nothing breakes the ſtaffe of our helpe but our leaning upon it. If wee truſt in our Covenant, wee have not made it with God, but wee have made it a God; And every God of mans making, is an Idol, and ſo <hi>nothing in the World:</hi> you ſee, pride in, or truſt to this Covenant will, make it an Idol, and then in doing all this, wee have done nothing, For <hi>an Idol is nothing in the World.</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 4.) And of nothing comes nothing. By over-looking to the meanes, wee loſe all; And by all our travayle ſhall bring forth nothing but wind It will not worke any deliverance in the Land. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>reſt not in the thing Done, but yet, up and be doing</hi> which is the laſt point, and my laſt motion about your walking in Covenant.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>walke induſtriouſly</hi> and diligently in this Covenant. You were counſelled before to ſtand to the Covenant, but take heede of ſtanding in it; ſtand, as that is oppoſed to defection, but if you ſtand
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155471:24"/> as that is oppoſed to action, you are at the next doore to falling. A Totall neglect is little better then totall Apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>We have made a perpetuall Covenant, never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, as was ſhewed out of the Prophet. It is a rule, that words in Scripture which expreſſe onely an Act of memory, include action and endeavours; When the young man is warned to <hi>remember his Creator in the dayes of his youth</hi> (Eccleſ. 12. 1.) Hee is alſo charged to love, and to obey him. And while we ſay, this Covenant is <hi>never to be forgotten,</hi> wee meane, the duties of it are ever to be purſued, and (to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of our power) fullfilled. As ſoone as it is ſayd that <hi>Joſiah</hi> made all the people <hi>ſtand to the Covenant,</hi> the very next words are, <hi>And the Inhabitants of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem did according to the Covenant of GOD, the GOD of their Fathers.</hi> 2 Chronicles 34. 32. They ſtood to it, but they did not (like thoſe <hi>Matthew</hi> 20. 6.) <hi>Stand all the day idle;</hi> they fell to worke pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. And ſo let us. Having layd this foundation, <hi>a ſure Covenant, now let us ariſe and build, and let our hands bee ſtrong.</hi> Doe not thinke that all is done, when this ſolemnity is done. It is a ſad thing to obſerve, how ſome, when they have lifted up their hands and written downe their names, thinke preſently their worke is over. They thinke, now ſurely they have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyed God and man, for they have ſubſcribed the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
            <p>I tell you nay, for when you have done taking the Covenant, then your worke begins. When you have done taking the Covenant, then you muſt proceede to acting the Covenant. When an appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice hath ſubſcribed his name, and ſealed his Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155471:25"/> doth hee then thinke his ſervice is ended? No, then hee knowes his ſervice doth begin. It is ſo here. Wee are all ſealing the Indentures of a ſacred and noble Apprentiſhip to God, to theſe Churches and Common-Wealths; let us then goe to our worke, <hi>as bound, yet free.</hi> Free to our worke, not from it; free in our worke, working from a principle of holy ingenuity, not of ſervility or conſtraint. The Lord threatens them with bondage and captivity, who will not bee ſervants in their Covenant, with readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and activity. <hi>I (ſayth the LORD) will give the men that have tranſgreſſed my Covenant, which have not performed the Words of the Covenant, which they had made before mee, when they cut the Calfe in twaine and paſſed betweene the parts thereof, The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of</hi> Judah, <hi>and the Princes of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>the Eunu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and the Prieſts, and all the people of the Land, which paſſed betweene the parts of the Calfe, I will even give them into the hand, of their Enemies, and into the hand of them that ſeeke their Life, and their dead Bodies ſhall bee meate to the Foules of the Ayre, and to the Beaſts of the Earth.</hi> Words that neede no Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke to preſſe them, nor any comment to explaine them: they are ſo plaine, that every one, may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, and ſo ſevere, that every one who either tranſgreſſes, or performes not, who doth any thing againſt, or nothing for the words of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, hath juſt cauſe to tremble at the reading of them, I am ſure, to feele them, will make him tremble. Seeing then our <hi>Princes,</hi> our <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> our <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and our people, have freely conſented to, written, and ſworne this Covenant; let us all in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places, up and be doing, that the Lord may be with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:155471:25"/> us, not ſit ſtill and doe nothing, and ſo cauſe the Lord to turne againſt us.</p>
            <p>You that are for Conſultation, goe to Counſell, you that are for Execution goe on to Acting, You that are for Exhorting the People in this Worke, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Exhortation, You that are Souldiers, draw your Swords, You that have Eſtates draw your Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, You that have ſtrength of body, lend your hands, and all you that have honeſt hearts, lend your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, your Cries, your Teares, for the proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of this great Worke, And the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper the Workes of all our hands, the Lord proſper all our handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
